Hello everyone, welcome to AdYouTube. Whenever
a person gets a job in a bank, the
first thing
people tell them is that now the
loan you get from the bank will be at a very low rate
or concessional rate, so
you're in for a treat. Now you can take a loan, buy a
car, buy a house, you'll have to pay very little
EMI, and the benefits you'll get will be
more than the general public. And
it's also true that people who work in banks, all
bank employees, get
many benefits regarding loans.
We'll discuss those benefits.
Before that, I'll give a disclaimer:
every bank has different policies. So,
whatever we'll discuss, we'll talk about a basic one.
I'll give you examples of some banks to see
what kind of
benefits you can get and how you
can plan your loans regarding
future expenses. Okay, so
multiple types of loans are
available to bank employees.  Whatever
loans you get for common customers, bank
employees also get the same, but there is a difference in the rate of
interest, there is a
difference in taxation, there is a
difference in tenure. So, we have different
types of facilities in which
festival advance vehicle loans are available, whether for two-
wheeler or four-wheeler, home loans are available,
overdraft facility is available, education loan is available,
loan is available against provident fund,
personal loans, multiple types of loans are available.
What is the most special thing in them, whatever loans
employees get, see, when the common people have to take a
loan from the bank, their
rate of interest is calculated, it is
calculated on compound interest, okay, it is
compound interest, but when you
take a loan as a bank employee from your own
bank, then how is the calculation done there on the
basis of simple interest, so the
biggest difference comes only here,
you all know about simple and compound interest, the
second thing is your
rate of interest.  Normally the
interest charge on 1 2 2 that is levied on the public is
charged one to two percent or less,
that if the common people are getting a loan at 10 percent
then you get a loan at 75 percent, that is
calculated on simple interest,
okay, so suppose if you want to take a house loan, if you want to take a
home loan then
when you take a loan from your bank, then first of all it will be
on simple interest, normal, if the public is
getting a loan at 9 percent, it is possible that you may get an interest at 7 percent, it
varies from bank to bank, but
you have to pay tax beyond that benefit,
suppose if you have
taken a loan of 40 lakhs and your installment is
22000 300 per month, okay, suppose your installment
is
22300, the same benefit, if
a common person had to take the loan, suppose his
installment would have been 40000, then this 22300 and this is
approximately here  The difference of Rs 17,700 will be
considered a benefit by the bank
and you will have to pay tax on it.
Whatever concessional part there is, you have to pay
tax on it, so it is considered a benefit,
but even after paying that tax, the
benefit you
get is quite a good benefit.
If you work in PNB
and you want to take a home loan, there
is a policy there that you should be a
confirmed employee with
completed five years of service and the
probationary period is also considered in this five year service.
Those with temporary services are
not included. Whereas
in Bank of India, as soon as you
complete your probationary period, you become
eligible for these benefits at concessional rates. So, some banks
demand a minimum of some years of service,
after which you will get loans at concessional rates.
You become eligible only after completing the probation. Now suppose I get
selected in the bank and
I need a loan after 10 days,
I will get the loan even then but then I will get it on the same
terms and conditions as the
general public gets. But
when I complete my probation or
in the case of some banks when I complete five years
of service, then I will get it at a
concessional rate. I may get it earlier also
but it will be given as normal as the rest of the public
gets. After that let's
talk about house loan.
Obviously there is a simple rate of
interest. After that you get the
benefit of 1 to 2 percent.
You get the loan at a lower rate of interest. So if we
talk about SB, then see which post you hold,
it also matters a lot. Sub staff
gets a loan of up to 30 lakhs, clerks get
up to 45 lakhs, officers up to the
rank of AGM get up to 60 lakhs.  You get a loan,
and the Deputy Director General of Police (DGM) or ABB
gets a loan of Rs 80 lakh. These
limits keep changing, and they
also vary from bank to bank. After that, the
interest rate also varies.
If your loan is up to Rs 40 lakh, it will be Rs
6.75. If your limit is Rs 40 lakh, it will be Rs
8, which is a much lower
rate of interest than the general public. Plus, when we look at the
difference between simple interest and compound interest, then there are
more
benefits. Whatever loan you get at a lower rate of
interest, it will be
considered a tax benefit. It will then be
considered an employment benefit, and
you will have to pay tax on it. So, whenever you
join a bank, definitely check all these terms and
conditions.
You
can do your planning accordingly. Even
in tax planning, you should consider all this. This is
a very good thing and which  What is provided is a
festive advance and here
in PNB you get around Rs 35,000 to Rs 125,000, the
scale
depends on your salary, normally your one month
salary is your basic pay, after adding special
allowance and DA,
you get a festive advance equal to your one month salary, so
if you want to take it before Diwali, before Durga Puja, then
you just have to submit an
application to your bank that I
want a festive advance, then you get one month's
salary extra and this
advance is interest free,
so if I have a demand of Rs 50,000, that means my
one month salary is Rs 50,000, I will get that much
festive advance and
I have to return this to the bank within 10 to 12 months, so
how does it get returned, it gets deducted from
my salary, okay, so the
advance of Rs 50,000 that I have received is a
festive advance.  The loan that I
can take once a year for any festival,
how will it be returned? Every month a
small amount of money will be deducted from my account.
It has to be returned within 10 to 12 months, it
depends from bank to bank. Okay,
in Bank of India, the
bank takes back all that money by deducting it from the salary within around 10 months.
Okay, so also, like there are a lot of
expenses around Diwali, so
this is a very good benefit that
bank employees get in the form of festive advance. Okay,
after that let's talk about vehicle loan.
Who will get the vehicle loan? How much will you get? It
depends on your scale. It
also depends on whether you already have EMIs or not. Okay, so what is the bank
's policy? How much loan is required? How much
tenure will it be? What is your credit rating?
What are the market conditions?
After considering all this, it is decided
how much loan you will get. The rest is
also decided according to your position.
Okay, so in Bank of India,
now  There is also a provision available that even during
your probation period,
which is initially I think of one year,
you can take a loan for a two-wheeler.
What is the situation with all other loans, they
either ask for a minimum of a few years of service,
2 years, 5 years. Some banks say that
you can take a loan as soon as your probation period is over.
But two-wheeler loan
is such that many banks allow
you to take a loan on a two-wheeler even during the probation period. So,
you can get a loan up to Rs 1.5 lakh for a two-wheeler. At an interest
rate of 5 to 7 percent, you can get a
four-wheeler loan up to Rs 15 lakh.
I think it is in Bank of India that you can get a loan up to Rs
18 lakh for hybrid vehicles.
And of course, they keep a margin
money in between. After that, if
your vehicle is worth Rs 1 lakh, then
you will be provided a loan of
approximately Rs 80-90 lakh.  The repayment period is 78 years
and in four wheeler the simple interest is 9 to 10%
so when you see the value of simple interest, it will
not be compounded, it will be
simple for you people, then that is a
very beneficial point,
so you can also take vehicle loan, whether it is a two
wheeler or a four wheeler, different
banks have different policies here,
okay after that you
get different types of loans, if you want education loan,
you will get it in education loan, your
provident fund, your provident fund gets
built up in a few years, so
even against that provident fund, if you
want to take a loan, you get a loan,
if you need overdraft facility
from your bank, you get that too, so suppose
I am an employee in a bank and I
need overdraft facility, then I will have a
separate account for overdraft,
but what will happen in it, then my salary will
come into my overdraft account, okay, then the money accordingly  There are
deductions from the salary,
credit debit keeps on going on, so the
overdraft facility also depends on your scale, on what
scale are you working, how many years have you been
working and what is your credit standing like?
Maintaining a good credit score is
very beneficial, whether you are a bank
employee, a common man, a bank
customer. If your credit rating is good, then
you get many benefits
and how can you maintain it well?
You should make timely repayments. It should not happen
that you have taken a loan from somewhere and you are
repaying it late.
Bank employees also get overdraft facility, which is
a very beneficial thing. Loan is available against PF,
education loan is also available. So
whenever your certain years of service
are completed or probation is completed,
then you can plan to
buy a car, you want to buy a vehicle, you
need a loan for a house, even it can happen that suppose it has been
20-25 years since I started serving in the bank.
Earlier I had taken a house loan
and I had repaid it,
now I have to renovate the same house, so can the same employee
take the same home loan for the second time in his lifetime, he can take it, there is no
problem in this, many
bank employees, suppose someone
is 50 years old, 55 years old, he
needs a home loan again, he has to do renovation, then
he can take it, if he wants to buy a plot,
build a house, renovate a house, you can get a home loan,
which means
if you see the maximum monetary benefit, it is
in home loan and in vehicle loan
you do not feel it at all because of that
you are paying simple interest, okay,
but now it is not like that if you have got the benefits then
you will keep taking loans,
no, the maximum amount that can be
deducted as EMI is 60 percent of your
salary, okay, so suppose if my salary is 1
lakh, then it is not like that I have taken so many loans
that every  Every month the bank will obviously
deduct my instalment and then give me my salary,
but that does not mean that I am getting Rs 80,000
deducted from Rs 1 lakh, Rs 90,000 is going towards EMI, the maximum allowed
in most banks is Rs 60,
my EMI will be deducted at Rs 60,
I should get my salary at Rs 40, so suppose I have taken a
home loan and I have
also taken a vocal loan and the instalment that is
going towards me is already Rs 60 of my salary,
then the bank will not give me any more facility
of the loan because
I am getting it deducted as an EMI at Rs 60, okay, so
whenever we have to plan or take a loan as a
bank employee, then we have to
see the conditions, so whenever you are joining a bank,
especially the new employees or the old
ones, then you get an idea about
what are the benefits, so the documents that your bank
gives you  Read them carefully
and then you can do your financial
planning okay so thatchi so
much